哈喽啊
Hey there!
这个YouTuber叫Xavier，是个开发者，字幕翻译给虫
My name is Xavier and as you might know I’m a developer.
但同时还是个SpaceX的粉丝，所以我在想，猎鹰9号、重型猎鹰和龙飞船
But I’m also a huge SpaceX fan and that got me thinking: what software and hardware
上硬件和软件是啥样的？
powers the Falcon 9, Falcon Heavy and Dragon?
我们首先看看飞船上的软件与硬件飞行时要面临哪些问题
Let’s first take a look at what challenges the hardware and software of a spacecraft
faces when it is being launched into space.
首先想要让东西进入地球轨道是很难的
First of all its very hard to get your craft into orbit around the earth.
火箭上震动会很剧烈，使得飞船本身
A launch on top of a rocket causes a lot of vibrations and that means that the craft itself
和上面的电子设备要能经受得住
and the electronics have to be able to withstand that.
而当你进了太空以后，难题就更多了
And once you get in orbit, you are welcomed by even more challenges.
太阳直射时龙飞船要忍受阳面的热量
Dragon for instance has to be able to cope with intense heat when it’s facing the sun
而到了地球背面则要忍受低温
but also intense cold when sunlight is blocked by earth.
这个温度变化在-150摄氏度到120摄氏度
These temperatures range from -150°C all the way up to 120°C
而对于电子设备，最大的问题来自于辐射
But the biggest problem for the electronics is radiation.
这种辐射来自于太阳、地球磁场，甚至来自外太阳系的粒子与射线
This radiation comes from high-energy particles that are ejected by our sun, particles trapped
这种辐射来自于太阳、地球磁场、甚至来自外太阳系的粒子与射线
in Earth’s magnetic field and even cosmic rays or particles from outside our solar system.
这些粒子会对飞船上的电子系统产生严重影响
These particles can have pretty severe effects on the systems inside a spacecraft.
其中最大的问题是比特反转
One of the biggest problems is whats called a bit flip.
这发生在高能粒子击中飞船的内存或者处理器时
This occurs when a high energy particle hits the memory or the processor of the spacecraft.
击中内存，可能把0打成1了，最终让一块内存崩溃
If it hits the memory it can cause a 0 to become a 1, essentially corrupting a part of the memory.
幸好SpaceX飞船上的软件能够检测到这种比特反转
Luckily though the software onboard SpaceX vehicles can detect these bit flips and fix
并通过奇偶校验修正之
the corrupted memory by using parity bits.
这点问题不大
No big deal.
然而当处理器被击中，则会导致计算结果完全错误
However when the processor is hit with radiation it can cause the result of a calculation to be completely incorrect.
举个简单的例子，我们让处理器计算10+10
To demonstrate this, let’s ask a processor to calculate 10+10.
二进制是这样的，结果是20(二进制的10100)
In binary that would look like this and the result is obviously 20.
毫无疑问
No surprises there!
但如果计算这个式子时发生了比特反转，我们看看结果会如何
But let’s now take a look at what happens when a bit flip occurs while performing this calculation.
还是让处理器计算10+10，但由于处理器内发生了比特反转
We still ask the processor to calculate 10 + 10 but because of the bit flip the processor
计算的内容就完全不是那回事了
is actually calculating something completely different.
而最终结果就是10+10=24
Right now it will say that 10 + 10 equals 24 because one of the bits flipped while running the calculations…
这种计算错误会对飞船造成极其严重的后果
Wrong calculations can have very severe effects on a spacecraft.
1996年阿里安5火箭首飞
This was demonstrated by the maiden flight of the Ariane 5 rocket in 1996.
它虽然没有遇到比特反转，但在飞行40秒时，火箭上的软件
It didn’t suffer from a bit flip, but 40 seconds into the flight, the rocket’s software
想把一个64位的数字存进16位的地址中，导致数字被截断
tried to put a 64 bit number into a 16 bit address causing the number to be truncated
从而得到一个完全不同的结果
and be completely different.
而火箭航电设备依然按照这个错误结果继续运算
The rocket’s avionics then continued to perform their calculations with this wrong
给虫玩KSP，用KOS控制发射的时候也遇到过这种情况……
然后飞着飞着突然改变航向，因为火箭以为自己飞错方向了
number and performed an abrupt course correction because it thought it was going to wrong way.
“因动压过大而解体”
火箭最终说白了就是被风吹散架了
The vehicle eventually broke up because the aerodynamic stress was simply too high.
回到SpaceX上来，他们如何处理辐射问题呢？
Now back to SpaceX: how do they handle the problem of radiation?
他们假设电子设备无法完全避免辐射
Well they assume that you can’t protect electronics completely from radiation and
这是他们系统设计的思路
they design their systems with this in mind.
他们不选昂贵的抗辐射零件，而是现成的零件
Instead of using expensive, radiation-hardened parts, SpaceX uses off-the-shelf components.
比如龙飞船
Let’s look at Dragon first.
根据John Muratore，前SpaceX载具保障说，每一艘龙飞船
According to John Muratore, previous director of SpaceX vehicle certification, each Dragon
有三台飞行计算机
is equipped with three flight computers.
每台飞行计算机由两个x86处理器驱动
Each of these flight computers is powered by a dual core x86 processor.
计算机本身并不是多核运算的
The computers however don’t use the multicore capability.
而是每个计算在每个核上独立进行一次，然后对比结果
Instead they execute each calculation on the two cores individually and compare the results.
所以三台计算机，每台两个核心，就有6个结果
So three flight computer with each a dual core processor can be seen as 6 independent
然后互相检查计算结果
computers that are constantly checking each others calculations.
如果某台计算机遭到比特反转，得出了错误结果
If one of the flight computers is hit with radiation and produces a wrong calculation,
其他的计算机就会发现
the others will spot it.
此时，那台出错的计算机就会自动重启，防止后续错误的发生
When that happens the malfunctioning computer will be rebooted automatically to prevent further errors.
重启后，计算机要进行一次“再同步”
After rebooting the computer has to perform whats called a re-sync.
要让它跟上飞船当前的任务，所以直接从另外两台计算机内存里复制内容然后继续跑程序
It has to get up to speed with what the vehicle is doing, so it copies the memory of the other
two computers and runs the same programs.
有点像电脑上“重启后恢复所有窗口”那个选项
A bit like rebooting your computer with the option to restore all your windows when you log back in.
而龙飞船还能应付这三台计算机同时全部被辐射击中的情况
Dragon can even handle a situation where all three of its computers are hit by radiation
虽然这种情况发生概率极低
at the same time although thats very unlikely to happen.
除了这三台飞行计算机，龙飞船还有另外18套系统，也都是三冗余设计
Besides 3 flight computers, Dragon has 18 other systems onboard that also use triple redundancy computers.
总共处理器数量就达到了54！
That brings the total amount of processors up to 54!
这还只是龙飞船上的
And that’s just for a single Dragon capsule.
除了龙飞船，猎鹰9号火箭也有冗余系统
But Dragon isn’t alone, also the Falcon 9 has redundant systems.
九台发动机，每台三部计算机，每部计算机三冗余
It has 3 computers for each engine (9 x 3) and triple-redundancy flight computer which
加上主控计算机，就是三十个处理器
means that it carries 30 processors.
至少2012年是这样的
At least that was the situation in 2012.
目前来看，猎鹰9为了着陆可能还要装更多的处理器
Right now it’s possible that Falcon 9 has even more processors to handle the landing.
这时候你可能会问……
Now at this point you might be thinking: hang on…
NASA真的允许SpaceX用普通民用的硬件设备吗？
Does NASA really allow SpaceX to use regular hardware components?
就是那种你我在淘宝都能买到的？
The ones you and I can buy on Amazon?
呃……还真就是！
Well actually yes!
NASA并不强求使用抗辐射设备
NASA doesn’t require the use of radiation-hardened components.
但他们会要求SpaceX广泛调查辐射对飞船的影响
Instead they require SpaceX to do extensive research into what effects the radiation can have on their spacecrafts.
如果知道了影响是怎样的，那就有解决办法了
If they know how they’ll be affected, they can compensate for it.
实际上这叫“耐辐射”设计，和“抗辐射”设计是不同的
In fact this is called a radiation-tolerant design and is different from a radiation-hardened design.
而且实际上NASA自己都不会在所有地方使用抗辐射的设备
In fact NASA itself doesn’t use radiation-hardened parts everywhere.
国际空间站上目前就是各种混合设备
The International Space Station for instance uses a mix of radiation-hardened parts but
一些控制甚至用的是普通的笔记本电脑
they also use regular laptops for some controls.
航天飞机上的一些设备也是耐辐射而不是抗辐射的
Even some parts on the Space Shuttle were radiation-tolerant instead of radiation-hardened.
回到SpaceX，他们怎么选零件呢？
But back to SpaceX: how do they select their parts?
两个条件，第一是要满足火箭、飞船的需求
Well they have two conditions: first of all the parts have to be capable enough to handle
这点不必多言；第二是要有合适的Tooling
their tasks - pretty obvious - and secondly, they take into account what tooling is available for that particular part.
Tooling指的是SpaceX能雇佣哪些人
Tooling determines what kind of people SpaceX can hire.
现成的硬件，通用性强，对应的软件与开发工具也有很多开发者在用
Off-the-shelf hardware is pretty generic and uses software and tooling that a lot of developers already know.
这让SpaceX不用费太大劲去找优秀的工程师
And that means that SpaceX has less trouble finding great engineers.
而抗辐射设备，本身用的就少，上面的编程语言和开发工具也鲜有人知
Radiation hardened parts however only work with special programming languages that few
使得SpaceX就很难招揽人才
people know, thus limiting the ability to hire new people.
同时现成的硬件还很便宜，SpaceX可以更广泛的进行测试
Off-the-shelf hardware is also cheaper and that allows SpaceX to extensively test these systems.
John Muratore说一个人办公桌上放过40片飞行计算机芯片用于测试
John Muratore said that at one point over 40 flight computers were sitting on people’s
desks for testing and development.
换又贵又少的芯片就没法这么做
You simply cannot do that with expensive and hard to come by hardware.
硬件说得差不多，那控制各种东西的软件又如何呢？
But enough about all this hardware, what about the software that controls everything?
呃SpaceX选择的操作系统是Linux
Well the operating system of choice at SpaceX is Linux.
工程师电脑上和火箭上都是Linux系统
It runs on the desktops of the engineers and powers its vehicles.
它们都用Linux能简化开发流程，同时也带来了整套齐全的工具
Using Linux everywhere allows them to streamline the development process and use the robust tools that come with it.
编程语言用的是C++，原因有二
The programming language of choice is C++ and they use it for two main reasons.
第一，C++用的人还算多，所以SpaceX招人方便
First it allows SpaceX to hire a lot of brilliant people because the language is still relatively popular.
第二，C++的生态很棒
Secondly, they benefits from the large C++ ecosystem.
不用费劲自己造轮子，好多工具像gcc、gdb都是现成的
No need to create custom software when you can just use tools that developers already
know like gcc, and gdb for instance.
但也不是只用Linux
But Linux isn’t the only platform that is being used.
他们还用Windows平台的LabView，一个图形化编程工具
They also use LabView a graphical programming tool that runs on Windows.
功能是在猎鹰9或者龙飞船飞行时可视化遥测数据
It is used to visualise telemetry that they get from a Falcon 9 or Dragon during flight.
地面小组用它监督重要数据
And ground teams use it to keep an eye on important metrics.
另外值得注意的是，SpaceX会尽量保持代码在不同载具间的通用性
Another interesting fact is that SpaceX tries to share as much code as possible between its vehicles.
最大的好处是某种载具的bug修正后，其他载具上的代码也能被push掉
The biggest advantage of this is that bug fixes for one vehicle are automatically pushed to the other vehicles as well.
还有，SpaceX很欢迎游戏开发者
Oh and another interesting fact is that game developers are usually a good fit for SpaceX
因为他们都已习惯在存储容量、计算性能受限的环境下开发
because they are used to writing code that runs in environments where memory and processing power are constrained.
最后说说SpaceX如何监测他们的软件和载具
The last thing we’ll take a look at is how SpaceX monitors their software and vehicles.
工程师会在所有能想到的地方加系统指标
Engineers are encouraged to add Metrics to everything they can think about.
当载具运行时，会收集所有log，然后会有程序分析这些log
When a vehicle is being used, all these logs are collected and analysed by programs who
一旦哪项超过安全阈值就会报警
raise an alarm if something is not within the safety margins.
所有系统指标都和运行时的源代码保存在一起
All these metrics are stored together with the source code that was running at that time.
一旦出现问题，SpaceX就能重现适当的情况
If something goes wrong with the vehicle, SpaceX can recreate the exact environment
再现问题并解决
to reproduce the problem and fix it.
最后，他们还用持续集成的方法，自动测试所有工程师提交的代码
And finally they are using continuous integration to automatically test all the code that is
being written by the engineers.
他们还会把猎鹰9用的所有零件都连上，从而模拟
They even have test stands with all the components of a Falcon 9 bolted on so they can simulate
一次完整的飞行过程，发现潜在问题
a complete flight to discover potential problems.
关于软硬件的更多细节也没了
More details about the used hardware and software aren’t really available and that’s because
因为美国政府认为这些是机密
the United States government considers it classified.
猎鹰9这种火箭其实就是能上太空的导弹
A rocket like the Falcon 9 is basically a missile that goes to space.
落入坏蛋手中不一定闹出什么幺蛾子
So in the wrong hands, the technology could be misused and cause harm.
但即使这样我们也能大致很好的了解SpaceX使用的软硬件设备
But even with limited information we got a pretty good view at what software and hardware
与这些设备在恶劣太空环境中要面对的问题
is being used at SpaceX and what challenges the teams face, considering the harsh environment in space.
就酱啦
That was it for this video!
喜欢记得点赞收藏投币分享关注啦
If you liked it, hit the thumbs up button and consider subscribing.
感谢观看
Also follow me on Twitter for more updates and as always: thank you so much for watching!